Finding Aid for Thomas Francis Papers
Bentley Historical Library
Thomas Francis Papers
1917-1975
1941-1969
Bentley Historical Library
Francis, Thomas, 1900-
851285 Aa 2
66 linear feet
2 oversize folders
The Thomas Francis Jr. collections consists of the personal and professional papers of one of the developers of the influenza and poliomyelitis vaccinations. Francis taught epidemiology at the School of Public Health and medical school from 1941 to 1969 and greatly influenced the direction of research in his field.
The papers of Thomas Francis, Jr. (Donor No. 4869 ) came to the library in two accessions. The major corpus of papers came from Francis' office in the U-M School of Public Health in 1970. A second smaller accession was received from the Francis family in 1989.
The collection is open to research except for patient records in boxes 23-24.
It is the policy of the library that records containing categories of personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. One such category is Client/Patient records which are restricted for 100 years from the date of creation. Boxes 23 and 24 of the Thomas Francis papers contain such Client/Patient material. Created in 1955, these material will be closed until 2055.
Researchers who wish to consult these records must apply to the University of Michigan Medical School Institutional Review Board (IRBMED) for permission. The IRBMED will determine any specific provisions for access to these records. The Bentley Library does not allow any duplication of these files.
Medical School Institutional Review Board
517 W. William, Argus I
Ann Arbor, MI 48103-4943
Email: irbmed@umich.edu
Phone: (734) 763 4768
Fax (734) 763 9603
Web site: http://www.med.umich.edu/irbmed/
Box 24 of the Thomas Francis collection also includes microfilm of the Field Trial registration schedules. These schedules which are arranged by state, then by school and class, lists the names of the students participating in the tests. These files are also closed with the exception that individuals who participated in the test may request copies of that schedule page containing their name.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Patient/client records are restricted for one-hundred (100) years from the date of their creation. The terms of use for particular records older than 100 years may require the research to sign a Patient/Client Access Agreement.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
Thomas Francis, Jr., 1900-1969, professor of epidemiology at the University of Michigan, 1941-1969, was best known for his work in the development of the influenza and poliomyelitis vaccinations. Educated at Allegheny College and Yale Medical School, Francis' work centered around the study of the causes of infectious disease, especially pneumonia, influenza, and poliomyelitis, and the development of serum treatments for these diseases.
The Twentieth Century witnessed a revolution in the manner in which scientific research was accomplished. The solitary figure in an underequipped laboratory gradually gave way to the research team comprised of specialists, established to solve some particular scientific problem, and funded with grants from foundations or agencies of the government. By mid-century, individual discoveries were still being made, but more common was cooperative research, where scientists freely exchanged information and built upon the work of their peers. During the period of Thomas Francis, Jr.'s greatest work, there was now a sense that common life-threatening problems required an all-out team effort and that claims for the discovery were less important than the fact that discovery was made. Leading the way in changing the way epidemiological research was performed was Thomas Francis, Jr.
Thomas Francis, Jr. was born July 15, 1900 in Gas City, Indiana, the son of Thomas and Elizabeth (Cadogan) Francis. He graduated with a B.S. from Allegheny College in 1921, then received his M.D. from Yale Medical School in 1925. After completing his residency at Yale, he went to the Rockefeller Institute Hospital where he worked in the Clinical Pneumonia Service under Rufus Cole and O.T. Avery. In 1936, he joined the staff of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation where he established study laboratories to work on the etiology and epidemiology of influenza. In 1938, he went to New York University College of Medicine as professor and chairman of the department of bacteriology.
In 1941, Francis came to the University of Michigan where he served as professor and chairman of the department of epidemiology in the newly established School of Public Health and professor of epidemiology in the Medical School. In 1947, he was appointed Henry Sewell Professor of Epidemiology. Francis remained at the University of Michigan until his death on October 1, 1969.
Francis' career centered around the study of the causes of infectious disease, especially pneumonia, influenza, and poliomyelitis, and the development of serum treatments for these scourges. While at the Rockefeller Foundation, Francis in his research on pneumonia created what he termed a "revolution in immunologic theory" when he demonstrated that antigens that produce antibodies were derived from polysaccharides of the pneumoccus. Prior to then, the accepted belief was that only proteins could function as antigens.
In 1934, Francis isolated the human influenza virus confirming the work of Smith, Andrewes and Laidlaw in England. He subsequently was able to establish the virus in mice and tissue culture. In 1940, he identified and was able to isolate influenza virus, Type B. The importance of his research was widely recognized. In 1941, he was appointed Director of the Commission on Influenza of the Army Epidemiological Board (its name was later changed to the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board). Here he established "listening posts" for the detection of influenza and conducted studies giving evidence that vaccination is effective against the epidemic strains of influenza. First in 1943, he developed a polyvalent vaccine that proved to be highly effective against influenza A in military personnel. Then in 1945, he demonstrated the effectiveness of vaccination against influenza B.
Throughout the 1940s, Francis and his colleagues undertook numerous studies pertaining to the epidemiology and immunology of poliomyelitis. The purpose of this work was to determine the virus' mode of entrance into a community and its spread thereafter. In 1954, the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis selected Francis to head up the Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center at the University of Michigan and to test the potency and effectiveness of the inactivated poliommyelitis vaccine developed by Jonas Salk. In what was until then the largest test of its kind, testing 1,800,000 children in forty-four states, Francis demonstrated the vaccine to be safe, potent and effective. On April 12, 1955, with Jonas Salk and Basil O'Connor of the National Foundation by his side, Francis announced to the world that a vaccine for paralytic polio had been found.
Francis was the author of numerous articles and a book on viral and Rickettsial diseases. He was additionally the recipient of various professional awards. For most of his career Francis was generous with his time, serving on the boards of private research organizations, professional organizations, and national and international governmental committees and institutes. A partial listing only includes the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, the National Academy of Science, the Atomic Bomb Casualty Committee, the Jane Coffin Childs Memorial Fund for Medical Research, and the Vaccine Development Committee.
Francis was a significant figure in the development and testing of vaccines to control the spread of two of the twentieth century's most devastating epidemical diseases - influenza and poliomyelitis. Interested in both theoretical and applied studies, Francis devoted his life to understanding the mechanisms of viral infections, and the development of means of resistance and prevention
Summary Contents List
General Correspondence, 1933-1969 - [Boxes 1-14]
Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center, 1953-1957 - [Boxes 14-24]
Armed Forces Epidemiological Board - [Boxes 28-38]
President's files, 1958-1960 -- [Boxes 28-31]
Commission on Influenza - [Boxes 32-38]
Organizations, 1939-1969 - [Boxes 25- 28, 39-56]
National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis - [Boxes 47-51]
University of Michigan, 1941-1969 - [Boxes 56-59]
Speeches, Articles, etc., 1928-1969 - [Boxes 59-63]
Topical Files, 1925-1967- [Boxes 63-64]
Personal/Biographical, 1917-1969 - [Boxes 65-66]
Important certainly for the study of influenza and poliomyelitis research, the Francis papers also document changes in the way scientific research, particularly medical research, was managed. In his correspondence files, the records from his work in combating influenza and poliomyelitis, and his participation in various professional societies, the researcher will find Francis interacting as a member of a scientific community, working with others, soliciting and exchanging views, and administering, when needed, vast programs of testing.
The Thomas Francis, Jr. papers have been arranged into seven series: General; Correspondence; Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center; Organizations; University of Michigan; Speeches, Articles, etc.; Topical Files; and Personal/Biographical. Specific topics covered in the collection are mentioned in the descriptions of individual series. In sum, the collection documents more thoroughly Francis' work since coming to the University of Michigan in 1941. Francis' fame rests upon his research and his heading-up of influenza and poliomyelitis testing programs. For some topics, use of the Francis papers will require of the researcher at least a basic level of knowledge of epidemiology or disease control. Other subjects, such as the administration of research projects and the ways in which information is transmitted within the scientific community are less specialized and capable of being understood by the informed layperson.
Parts of the Francis papers have not yet been completely processed. Most of these subseries pertain to Francis' organizational commitments and to his membership on various boards and commissions. Types of records in these unprocessed subseries consist of minutes of meetings and procedural records. These unprocessed records are indicated on the finding aid along with the bulk size of the subseries.
Epidemics.; Epidemiology.; Influenza.; Medicine -- Michigan.; Poliomyelitis.; Poliomyelitis vaccine.; Physicians -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Public health -- United States.; Awards.; Photographs.; Andrewes, C. H. (Christopher Howard); Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission.; Francis, Thomas, 1900-; National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis.; O'Connor, Basil, 1892-1972.; Salk, Jonas, 1914-1995.; United States. Armed Forces Epidemiological Board.; United States. Commission on Influenza.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; Francis, Thomas, 1900-
- General Correspondence, 1933-1969; 13.5 linear feet
  General Correspondence, 1933-1969 (13.5 linear feet). This series consists of eight dated subseries arranged alphabetically. The dates of the subseries vary in length and do not always correspond to either an academic or calendar year. The dating of the subseries are also not rigid as occasional letters from either an earlier or later subseries might be found. The arrangement of the files is alphabetical usually by an individual's name but sometimes by his/her organizational affiliation. Correspondents consist mostly of Francis' professional colleagues, students, members of the scientific community in general, and lay people who recognized Francis for his many contributions. Topics might be highly scientific or just pertaining to publications, conference meetings, or "keeping in touch" communications with his academic colleagues.
  - 1933-June 1941
    - A-R; include files for (Box 1)
      - American Museum of Health (Box 1)
      - Andrewes, C.H (Box 1)
      - Baum, H. H.L (Box 1)
      - Beck, M. Dorothy (Box 1)
      - Calco Chemical Company (Box 1)
      - Duncan, Charles Henry (Box 1)
      - Fan mail (Box 1)
      - Francis, Thomas
        - Personal (Box 1)
          (with family)
        - Concerning publications (Box 1)
      - Fremont-Smith, Frank (Box 1)
      - Hare, Ronald (Box 1)
      - Influenza virus (Box 1)
        (correspondence concerning)
      - Jones, T. Duckett (Box 1)
      - Kerr, William J (Box 1)
      - Kuttner, Ann G (Box 1)
      - Lape, Esther E (Box 1)
      - MacNider, William (Box 1)
      - Metropolitan Life Insurance Co (Box 1)
      - Milk Commission of the Medical Society of the County of New York (Box 1)
      - Public Health Relations Committee (Box 1)
        (of New York Academy of Medicine)
      - Rockefeller, Nelson (Box 1)
        (also about health of Mrs. John D. Rockefeller)
      - Russell, F.F (Box 1)
    - S-Z; include files for (Box 2)
      - Shope, Richard E (Box 2)
      - Stokes, Joseph (Box 2)
  - July 1941-December 1944
    - A-M; include files for (Box 2)
      - Kerato Conjunctivitis (Box 2)
        (report about)
    - N-Z; include files for (Box 3)
      - Poliomyelitis, 1941-1942; 2 folders (Box 3)
        (letters to county health officers)
      - Sarvis, Lewis J. (Box 3)
        (re U-M School of Public Health building)
      - Specimens mailed (Box 3)
  - January 1945-December 1947
    - A-F; include files for (Box 3)
      - Carworth Farms (Box 3)
        (supplier of laboratory animals)
      - Fan mail (Box 3)
      - Kerato Conjunctivitis (Box 3)
    - F-Z; include files for (Box 4)
      - Francis, Thomas
        - Personal (Box 4)
        - Michigan State Board of Registration (Box 4)
        - University of Michigan (Box 4)
          (negotiations with)
      - International Congress for Microbiology (Box 4)
      - International Congress of Pediatrics (Box 4)
      - Penner, L.R (Box 4)
      - Pickels, E.G (Box 4)
      - Poliomyelitis (Box 4)
        (miscellaneous; includes some 1944)
      - Public Health Laboratory (Box 4)
        (personnel for)
      - Salk, Jonas (Box 4)
        (includes correspondence back to 1941)
      - Vaughan, Henry F (Box 4)
      - Wyckoff, Ralph W.G (Box 4)
  - January 1948-December 1950
    - A-R; include files for (Box 5)
      - Brewer, J.H. (Box 5)
        (re merodicein study)
      - Darvisul (Box 5)
      - Kohn, Erwin (Box 5)
        (Unitarian mission to Europe)
      - Molitor, Hans (Box 5)
        (Merck Institute)
      - Monkeys (Box 5)
        (Okatie Farms suppliers)
    - S-Z (Box 6)
  - January 1951-June 1955
    - A-K; include files for (Box 6)
      - Baron, Samuel (Box 6)
        (re his research at the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis)
      - Hartman, Frank W. (Box 6)
        (re Symposium on the Dynamics of Virus Infections, 1953)
    - L-Z; include files for (Box 7)
      - Lape, Esther Everett (Box 7)
      - Leprosy. International Congress in Madrid, Spain (Box 7)
      - Medical education. First International Congress on Medical Education, 1953 (Box 7)
      - Microbiology. Sixth International Congress for Microbiology, 1953 (Box 7)
      - Nomenclature. Conference on Virus and Rickettsial Classification and Nomenclature, 1952 (Box 7)
  - July 1955-June 1959
    - A-E (Box 7)
    - F-Q; include files for (Box 8)
      - Fluoridation (Box 8)
      - Grist, N.R. (Box 8)
        (regarding)
      - Hypertension. Regional Conference on Hypertension, 1957 (Box 8)
      - Ishida, Nakao (Box 8)
      - Koller, Siegfried (Box 8)
        (includes manuscript of his article)
      - Kunin, Calvin (Box 8)
      - Lape, Esther Everett (Box 8)
      - Monkeys (Box 8)
        (Okatie Farm)
      - National Drug Company (Box 8)
      - National Institutes of Health (Box 8)
      - New York Academy of Sciences: Conference on "Viruses in Search of a Disease", 1956 (Box 8)
      - Poliomyelitis
        - Letters received in response to receipt of polio vaccine report (Box 8)
        - Poliomyelitis Vaccine Project Demonstration Child Health Conference, 1955 (Box 8)
        - Ad hoc Committee on Poliomyelitis Vaccine, 1955-1956 (Box 8)
    - R-Z; include files for (Box 9)
      - World Health Organization, 1953-1956 (Box 9)
        (includes papers)
  - July 1959-1966
    - A-D; include files for (Box 9)
      - Ahrens, E.H., 1961 (Box 9)
        (re arteriosclerosis discussion group)
      - Allegheny College (Box 9)
      - Animal care legislation (Box 9)
      - Atlas Powder Company (Box 9)
      - Beebe, Gilbert W (Box 9)
      - Bell, Joseph (Box 9)
      - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (Box 9)
      - Cameron, George M (Box 9)
      - Cockburn, Charles (Box 9)
      - Communicable Disease Control (Box 9)
      - Conard, Robert A. (Box 9)
      - Connecticut Medicine (Box 9)
      - Cowan, John A (Box 9)
      - Culbertson, C.G (Box 9)
      - Dingle, John (Box 9)
    - D-M; include files for (Box 10)
      - Doisy, Edward A (Box 10)
      - Drescher, Joachim (Box 10)
      - Ferris, Blake E (Box 10)
      - Flood, Merrill M (Box 10)
      - Fox, John (Box 10)
      - Galdston, Iago (Box 10)
      - Gerard, Ralph W (Box 10)
      - Gilliam, Alexander G. (Box 10)
      - Henneberg, Georg (Box 10)
      - Hill, Austin B (Box 10)
      - Hill, Lister (Box 10)
      - Hilleman, M.R (Box 10)
      - Hobson, Derek (Box 10)
      - Huebner, Robert J (Box 10)
      - Humphrey, Hubert (Box 10)
      - International health legislation (Box 10)
      - Jensen, Keith (Box 10)
      - Lasker Award (Box 10)
      - Loosli, Clayton G (Box 10)
      - McCollum, Robert W (Box 10)
      - McFarland, Ross A (Box 10)
      - McKeown, Thomas (Box 10)
      - McNinch, Joseph H (Box 10)
    - M-S; include files for (Box 11)
      - Michigan Dept. of Public Health. Technical Committee on Immunization (Box 11)
      - Michigan State Medical Society (Box 11)
      - Miller, H.H (Box 11)
      - Mizutani, Hiromichi (Box 11)
      - Modell, Walter (Box 11)
      - Mori, Ryoichi (Box 11)
      - Mulder, J (Box 11)
      - National Library of Medicine (Box 11)
      - Okatie Farms (Box 11)
        (suppliers of laboratory animals)
      - Perkins, F.T (Box 11)
      - Perrott, George (Box 11)
      - Perspectives in Biology and Medicine (Box 11)
      - Plasma (Box 11)
        (includes earlier materials)
      - Polio suspect (Box 11)
      - Poliomyelitis Control, Surgeon General's Committee on (Box 11)
      - Price, David (Box 11)
      - Price, Winston (Box 11)
      - Robinson, William D (Box 11)
      - Rockefeller Institute (Box 11)
      - Rose, Bram (Box 11)
      - Schering Corporation (Box 11)
      - Science. American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 11)
      - Scudder, Harvey I (Box 11)
      - Shannon, James A (Box 11)
      - Slepushkin, A.N (Box 11)
      - Shilling, Charles W (Box 11)
      - Smorodintsev, Anatol A (Box 11)
    - T-Z; include files for (Box 12)
      - Thomas, Charles C (Box 12)
      - Tillett, William S (Box 12)
      - Uhr, Jonathan W (Box 12)
      - Upjohn Company (Box 12)
      - Valkenburg, Hans A (Box 12)
      - Vaughan, Henry F
        - Correspondence (Box 12)
        - Vaughan portrait and testimonial (Box 12)
        - TF manuscript of tribute to Vaughan on presentation of portrait, 1964 (Box 12)
      - Webster, R.G (Box 12)
      - Wedum, A.G. (Box 12)
        (Porton-Henderson equipment chamber)
      - Weir, John M (Box 12)
      - WHO Influenza Centers (Box 12)
      - Yale Sesquicentennial Celebration, 1961 (Box 12)
  - 1966-1969
    (includes earlier papers)
    - A-M; include files for (Box 12)
      - Allegheny College (Box 12)
      - American Medical Association (Box 12)
      - Archives of Environmental Health (Box 12)
      - Baroyan, O.V (Box 12)
      - Becker, Maurice (Box 12)
      - Beierwaltes, William (Box 12)
      - Blaskovic, Dino (Box 12)
      - Borecky, Ladislav (Box 12)
      - Conn, Jerome (Box 12)
      - Downie, Allan W (Box 12)
      - DuPont Co., 4 folders (Box 12)
        (amantadine research)
      - Fazekas de St. Groth, Stephen (Box 12)
      - Fleming, Robben W (Box 12)
      - Fukumi, Hideo (Box 12)
      - Giovanardi, Augusto (Box 12)
      - Goodner Memorial Fund Committee (Box 12)
      - Gordon, Irving (Box 12)
      - Grayston, Thomas (Box 12)
      - Haas, Richard (Box 12)
      - Hemphill, F.M (Box 12)
      - Hers, J.F (Box 12)
    - H-S; include files for (Box 13)
      - Horsfall, Frank L., Jr (Box 13)
      - Howe, Howard (Box 13)
      - Huggins, Charles (Box 13)
      - Ishida, Nakao (Box 13)
      - Jacob, Edwin J (Box 13)
      - Langmuir, Alex D (Box 13)
      - Lasker Award (Box 13)
      - Lennette, Edwin H (Box 13)
      - Loh, Philip (Box 13)
      - MacLeod, Colin (Box 13)
      - Melnick, Joseph L (Box 13)
      - Michigan Dept. of Public Health. Technical Committee on Immunization (Box 13)
      - Milliken, William (Box 13)
      - Mudd, Stuart (Box 13)
      - Murray, Roderick (Box 13)
      - National Communicable Disease Center (Box 13)
      - National Foundation (Box 13)
      - National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases. Rubella Virus Vaccine trial (Box 13)
      - National Institutes of Health (Box 13)
      - National Institute of Mental Health. Center for Epidemiolgic Studies (Box 13)
      - National Institute of Neurolgic Diseases and Blindness-Rubella (Box 13)
      - Nixon, Richard (Box 13)
        (reaction to speech)
      - Ochoa, Severo (Box 13)
      - Ortlieb, Rene J (Box 13)
      - Paffenbarger, Ralph (Box 13)
      - Page, Irvine (Box 13)
      - Paul, John R (Box 13)
      - Postlethwaite, Roy (Box 13)
      - Rammelkamp, Charles H (Box 13)
      - Reiff, Guy G (Box 13)
      - Rous, Peyton (Box 13)
      - Salk, Jonas (Box 13)
      - Science (Box 13)
        (periodical)
      - Shope, Richard E (Box 13)
      - Smadel, Joseph (Box 13)
        (also concerns Smadel memorial)
      - Smadel Lecture, 1967 (Box 13)
      - Soloviev, Vanlentine (Box 13)
      - Stamler, Jeremiah (Box 13)
      - Starling, Frank M (Box 13)
      - Stern Symposia on Perspectives in Virology (Box 13)
      - Sternberg Award (Box 13)
      - Stewart, Gordon (Box 13)
      - Stock, C. Chester (Box 13)
    - T-Z; include files for: (Box 14)
      - U.S. Public Health Service (Box 14)
      - Vaughan, Henry F (Box 14)
      - Wenner, Herbert (Box 14)
      - Wilkins, Robert (Box 14)
      - Wood, Harrison (Box 14)
      - Woodward, Theodore (Box 14)
      - World Health Organization Expert Committee on Respiratory Viruses (Box 14)
        (A.M. Payne)